<!--
This file is to record the changes in the ELK project that will be reported
in the release history and release announcements. It is reasonable to keep
changes relatively high level to be understandable by the users but still
reflect the main changes made in the project.
Please refer to the following link regarding the format of this file:
http://maven.apache.org/plugins/maven-changes-plugin/changes.html
Please avoid making line breaks and tabulation in the description as those 
will appear in the produced result. 
-->
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/changes/1.0.0"
	xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
	xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/changes/1.0.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/changes-1.0.0.xsd">
	<properties>
		<title>ELK Reasoner Project</title>
	</properties>
	<body>
	    <release version="${release.version}" date="${buildDate}" description="Changes since the last release">
		</release>
		<release version="0.4.3" date="2016-01-11" description="Third maintenance relase after the fourth public release">
			<action dev="petesko" type="update">
				Switch to the OWL API version 4. Dropping support for OWL API 3 and Protege 4.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="0.4.2" date="2015-03-03" description="Second maintenance relase after the fourth public release">
			<action dev="yevgeny" type="update">
				ELK can now be interrupted from the OWL API and Protege during the initial ontology loading stage.				
			</action>
			<action dev="yevgeny" type="update">
				Updated the mechanism of interrupting reasoner computations due to removal of interrupt exceptions from the code.				
			</action>
			<action dev="pavel" type="fix" issue="27">
				Fixed a problem causing runtime exception to be thrown with Protege 5 beta 15 due to the class loader of Apache Felix reacting on interrupt exceptions used for communication with elk worker threads.				
			</action>
			<action dev="pavel" type="fix" issue="24">
				Fixed a bug reporting direct subclasses of owl:Thing when owl:Thing has (redundant) asserted subclasses.				
			</action>
	    </release>
	    <release version="0.4.1" date="2013-08-15" description="First maintenance relase after the fourth public release">
			<action dev="yevgeny" type="fix" issue="23">
				Fixed a bug when querying equivalent classes of complex class expressions may include auxiliary classes.				
			</action>
			<action dev="yevgeny" type="fix" issue="20">
				Fixed a bug when changes were loaded in buffering mode without calling flush().
			</action>
			<action dev="pavel" type="fix" issue="22">
				Fixed improper handling of parsing exceptions in presence of SWRL rules.
			</action>
			<action dev="pavel" type="fix">
				Numerous javadoc issues fixed.
			</action>			
	    </release>
	    <release version="0.4.0" date="2013-07-20" description="Fourth public release">
			<action dev="pavel" type="add"  issue="9">
				Incremental reasoning. The reasoner can incrementally update the inferred class and instance hierarchies after adding, removing, or modifying axioms. Changes in axioms which may affect the property hierarchy or property chains, e.g., SubObjectPropertyOf, TransitiveObjectProperty, etc., will still trigger full re-classification.
			</action>
			<action dev="yevgeny" type="add" issue="10">
				Queries of complex class expressions (satisfiability checking, retrieval of equivalent classes, subclasses, and superclasses) are now supported through incremental reasoning.
			</action>			
			<action dev="yevgeny" type="add">
				Support for positive occurrences of negation (ObjectComplementOf) and negative occurrences of disjunctions (ObjectUnionOf).
			</action>
			<action dev="yevgeny" type="update">
				New rule engine under the hood that provides a general way of specifying and registering composition and decomposition rules for various language features.
			</action>
			<action dev="yevgeny" type="update">
				New reasoning stage management to keep track of dependencies between reasoning stages and of their execution.
			</action>
			<action dev="yevgeny" type="add">
				Support for explanation and DL query features in Protege through queries for complex class expressions.
			</action>						
			<action dev="pavel" type="update">
				The OWL 2 FSS parser now runs lexer and tokenizer in parallel threads.
			</action>
			<action dev="pavel" type="add">
				Incremental reasoning mode can be enabled/disabled from the Reasoner Preferences panel in Protege.
			</action>						
			<action dev="pavel" type="fix" issue="12">
				Fix the location of examples in the owlapi-library distribution package as described in the README.txt file
			</action>
			<action dev="pavel" type="fix" issue="14">
				ELK now tracks changes in axioms which belong to imported ontologies. Also it doesn't log warnings for changes in ontologies outside the import closure.
			</action>
			<action dev="yevgeny" type="fix" issue="18">
			    Fixed conversion of double inverse object properties from OWL API				
			</action>
	    </release>
	    <release version="0.3.2" date="2013-01-17" description="Second maintenance release after the third public release">
			<action dev="yevgeny" type="fix">
				Fixed an issue causing a deadlock with many workers in the saturation stage. 
			</action>
			<action dev="yevgeny" type="update">
				Updated dependencies for OWL API to v.3.4.2.
			</action>	    
	    </release>
		<release version="0.3.1" date="2012-08-30" description="First maintenance relase after the third public release">				    
			<action dev="yevgeny" type="fix" issue="7">
				Fixed NoSuchElementException when loading imported ontologies through OWLAPI that have no axioms. 
			</action>
			<action dev="pavel" type="fix">
				Fixed a bug with incorrect handling of lexical errors during parsing of OWL2 FSS files with the native ELK's parser.
			</action>			
			<action dev="pavel" type="update">
				An improved testing of class and instance taxonomies via mock taxonomy objects and specific validators (e.g., for acyclicity and transitive reduction).
			</action>
			<action dev="yevgeny" type="update">
				Updated project configurations to comply with Maven Central requirements.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="0.3.0" date="2012-07-19" description="Third public release">			
			<action dev="frantisek" type="fix" issue="6">
				Fixed NullPointerException when loading ontologies with ObjectMinCardinality and ObjectExactCardinality constructors that have empty fillers.
			</action>
			<action dev="frantisek" type="fix" issue="1">
				Fixed NullPointerException when querying the reasoner for a class not occurring in the signature of the ontology.
			</action>
			<action dev="markus" type="add">
				Reporting of reasoner warnings in Protege user interface.
			</action>			
			<action dev="frantisek" type="add">
				Support for owl:Nothing and DisjointClasses axioms.
			</action>
			<action dev="frantisek" type="add">
				Support for ReflexiveObjectProperty axioms.
			</action>
			<action dev="frantisek" type="add">
				Support for individuals in ClassAssertion, ObjectPropertyAssertion, and ObjectHasValue.
			</action>
			<action dev="frantisek" type="add">
				Support for consistency checking and instance retrieval queries for named classes.
			</action>
			<action dev="pavel" type="add">
				A new infrastructure for automated testing of ontology loading, printing, generation of taxonomies, and realization. 
			</action>
			<action dev="markus" type="update">
				A generic infrastructure for specification and registration of reasoning rules.
			</action>
			<action dev="yevgeny" type="add">
				A mechanism for interruption and restarting of reasoning tasks.
			</action>
			<action dev="yevgeny" type="update">
				A reorganized infrastructure for reasoning tasks, reasoning stages, and reasoning engines.
			</action>			
		</release>
		<release version="0.2.0" date="2011-10-25" description="Second public release">
			<action dev="frantisek" type="fix" issue="5">
				Fixed tokenization of IRIs containing reserved words in the built-in parser.
			</action>
			<action dev="frantisek" type="fix" issue="4">
				Fixed grammar for non-negative integers in the built-in parser.
			</action>
			<action dev="frantisek" type="fix" issue="3">
				Fixed grammar for ObjectOneOf in the built-in parser.
			</action>
			<action dev="markus" type="fix" issue="2">
				Close all threads immediately when OWLReasoner.dispose() is called.
			</action>
			<action dev="markus" type="add">
				Support for object property domain axioms.
			</action>
			<action dev="frantisek" type="add">
				Support for object property chain inclusion axioms.
			</action>
			<action dev="markus" type="update">
				Re-engineering of ELK OWL object hierarchy using interfaces instead of (abstract) classes.
			</action>
			<action dev="yevgeny" type="add">
				Protege plugin: support for Protege 4 auto-update feature.
			</action>
			<action dev="yevgeny" type="add">
				Automated project distribution management through Apache Maven.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="0.1.0" date="2011-07-19" description="First public release">
			<action dev="yevgeny" type="add">
				Support for classification of EL ontologies with role hierarchies and transitive roles.
			</action>
			<action dev="yevgeny" type="add">
				Classification can run concurrently and make use of the available multiple processors and cores.
			</action>
			<action dev="yevgeny" type="add">
				Preliminary implementation of the OWL API and Protege reasoner interfaces.
			</action>
			<action dev="yevgeny" type="add">
				OWL API: Support for dynamic loading of changes in ontologies.
			</action>
		</release>
	</body>
</document>